Well, apparently, the United States just
did not get its fill of Cold War era
stalemates after pretty much laying an
egg in the Korean War.
I want some more. So, that means it's
time to talk about the Vietnam War. So,
if you're ready to get them brain cows
milked a Gulf of Tonkin Resolution
style, then let's get to it. Okay, so
let's jump right in and talk about the
causes of the Vietnam War, and there are
two major developments here that you're
going to need to remember. First of all,
the war was caused by the fear of the
spread of communism and the US policy of
containment. In case you've been napping
through the last couple of videos, let
me Heim-xplain that up real quick for
you. So, recall that a key feature of
the Cold War was the ideological contest
between the democratic capitalism of the
United States and the authoritarian
communism of the Soviet Union. put it
mildly, US officials weren't all that
fond of those godless commies spreading
their ideology on the world stage. And
so, US officials adopted the policy of
containment to prevent the spread of
communism, which, you know, was exactly
what it sounds like. And that was part
of a larger plan to fight communism that
was laid out in a top secret document
known as NSC 68, which was responsible
for massive military buildup and the
military-industrial complex that I
talked about in the last couple of
videos. Anyway, President Harry Truman
homed the idea of containment when he
articulated the Truman Doctrine, which
said that the United States would offer
financial and military aid to any nation
that was threatened by the infiltration
of communism. And that containment
policy led to conflicts in the Korean
War, the Middle East, Asia, Europe, and
Latin America. But, for the purposes of
this video, I'll focus on the
application of containment in Asia
because that's how we're going to arrive
in the war in Vietnam. Okay, and then
the second cause of the war was the
global phenomenon of decolonization
after World War II. And since I flapped
my mouth hole prodigiously about this a
few videos ago, I'll keep it short here.
After World War II, colonized nations
all over the world either fought for or
negotiated their independence from their
former European imperial rulers. And
into that environment in which dozens of
newly independent states were being
born, the Soviets and the Americans
eagerly sought to influence these new
states to bring them into their own
sphere of influence. And such was the
case, my dear pupil, with Vietnam. And I
admit I'm itching to tell you about it,
but first, let's just acknowledge
something that you very much don't want
to admit, namely that the stinking A
push national exam is coming up quick,
fast, and in a hurry. And so, if you
need help getting a five on that you
might want to check out my A push
Heimler review guide, which has
everything you need to study as fast as
possible. So, get that clicky finger out
and check that link in the description.
Okay, so by 1954, the decades-long
struggle of the Vietnamese against their
French colonizers had come to an end,
and the Vietnamese were at long last
free. But, here comes the Cold War to
drop an absolute dump on that freedom.
And because this occurred right at the
same moment when the Red Scare and
McCarthyism was reaching its peak
hallucinogenic fever dream, the US was
real motivated to make sure Vietnam
didn't end up under communist control,
especially
since China had recently become
communist. And so, at the Geneva
Conference, which outlined the terms of
Vietnamese peace, the United States, the
Soviet Union, and Communist China agreed
that Vietnam would be temporarily
divided at the 17th parallel until
nationwide elections could be held. And
that reflected the geographical division
of two rival factions that had been
steadily growing during the war for
independence. So, the North Vietnamese
established a communist government under
the leadership of our boy Ho Chi Minh
and immediately began implementing
communist policies like land
redistribution and all the rest. And
this government, to no one's surprise,
got metric buttloads of help and support
from the Soviet Union and Communist
China. But, in the South Vietnamese
established an anti-communist
government, which was heavily supported
by the United States. And can you
believe it, the North Vietnamese wanted
to unite the entire country under a
communist regime, while the South
Vietnamese wanted to unite the entire
country under their own anti-communist
regime. I mean, who could have seen that
coming? Anyway, as it happened, there
was a small but disgruntled group of
communist Vietnamese sympathizers who
lived in South Vietnam, and by the
mid-1950s, they had launched a series of
guerrilla attacks against the South
Vietnamese government. And that act
started what should have been a nice,
tidy civil war between the northern and
southern Vietnamese. However, because
communist and anti-communist were
fighting, the conflict quickly became a
proxy war between the United States and
the Soviet Union with support from
China. And look, if this smells an awful
lot like the exact stinking conditions
that led to the Korean War, well, then
your sniffer is working just fine. And
you'd think that American policymakers
would have learned their lesson about
throwing guns and money into smaller
regional conflicts that ultimately ended
in stalemate, but
no. You see, President Eisenhower and
then Kennedy after him articulated and
embraced what was known as the domino
theory, and that had a way of making
them forget whatever lessons they
learned from Korea. Essentially, it said
that if communists gained control of one
Asian regime, then every other country
in the region would fall to communism
like a series of socialist dominoes
crashing into one another. And so, both
the Soviets and the United States became
heavily involved in this new proxy war.
Okay, and so now, let me give you the
briefest of sketches for how the war
itself actually went. So, US involvement
in Vietnam escalated step by step, and
that is the key word to remember,
escalation. It began with President
Eisenhower sending several hundred US
military advisers and approving billions
of dollars of aid sent to South Vietnam,
largely for the purpose of enabling land
reforms that would stabilize their new
government. However, the South
Vietnamese president, Ngo Dinh Diem,
went ahead and spent a huge chunk of
that money on building up his military
and cracking down on Buddhists and
suspected communists and just generally
consolidating his own power. And then,
by the time John F. Kennedy took office,
it was apparent that the situation was
seriously deteriorating, he sent more
military advisers in order to try to
bring some order to the situation. Like,
a little more escalation will surely do
the trick. But, for various reasons, the
situation got worse, and so Kennedy
authorized a coup to oust Diem and
install a military government in its
place. But, northern communists appealed
to southern peasants, promising
much-desired land reforms if they would
fight against the new government in the
South, and that created even more
problems for the US. But then, in 1963,
Kennedy was assassinated, and Lyndon B.
Johnson took office and inherited the
mess in Vietnam. And it was a sticky
situation because all things being
equal, Johnson should have just cut
American losses in Vietnam and exited
the situation. Like, nothing seemed to
be working, and the conflict was rapidly
turning into a quagmire in which very
little progress could be made. However,
Johnson, just like his Cold War
predecessors, refused to end the
conflict for many reasons, not least of
which he wanted to avoid the criticism
that he was soft on communism, which was
the ultimate insult of the era. But even
so, Johnson put his patient pants on and
waited for an opportune moment to
escalate US involvement in Vietnam even
further. And right on schedule, that
fortuitous moment came in 1964 in the
Gulf of Tonkin Incident. And long story
short, two North Vietnamese gunboats
attacked a US Navy ship in the Gulf of
Tonkin, and then two days later, it was
reported that another US ship was
attacked, but not damaged. However,
there was a great deal of confusion over
whether the ships were actually attacked
by the North Vietnamese or not. In fact,
later it was discovered that the first
attack wasn't all that serious, but the
second attack was straight-up
fabricated. But, it didn't matter
because Johnson seized this moment as
the justification to get his own
escalation on and press for victory. And
so, Congress passed the Gulf of Tonkin
Resolution, which essentially gave the
president unlimited power to make
decisions about US military involvement
and strategy in Vietnam. And after that,
whatever reservations Johnson had about
escalating US involvement in Vietnam was
summarily flushed down the toilet. And
when I tell you it was a hard flush, I
am not lying. For example, in 1963, the
US had 16,000 troops in Vietnam, but by
1968, it was over half a million. And
surely, with such overwhelming pressure
from the most powerful military on God's
green earth, the war is going to be over
flash. But, no matter how many troops
Johnson sent there, pressure on the
North Vietnamese proved ineffective time
after time since communist forces
largely waged a more hidden guerrilla
warfare that was difficult to counter
with traditional military strategies.
But, that's not the end of the
escalation story. No, after Johnson left
office, Richard Nixon inherited the war,
and while he began by de-escalating it,
he eventually followed the same path by
further escalating conflict with more US
troops. However, by that point, public
support for the war was largely against
continuing involvement in the conflict.
And contributing to that resistance was
the devastating surprise attack from the
North Vietnamese known as the Tet
Offensive. And following that disaster,
Nixon devised a plan known as
Vietnamization, which called for the
removal of US troops by handing
responsibility over for the continuing
fight to the South Vietnamese
themselves. However, Nixon further
escalated the conflict by ordering a
bombing campaign in Cambodia, and public
opinion concerning the war shrank to new
lows. And therefore, widespread protests
erupted across college campuses in the
United States, and a sizable number of
Vietnam veterans protested the war as
well. And what was worse, in 1972, the
New York Times Washington Post jointly
released the Pentagon Papers, which
further turned public opinion against
the war. They were full of leaked
classified documents that proved that
Kennedy, Johnson, and Nixon had all lied
to the public about the origin and
ongoing success of the war. And that led
to a profound credibility gap for the
presidency. And that gap was only
further widened by television reports
coming out of Vietnam, which always
seemed to contradict the rosy picture of
the conflict painted by the president.
Anyway, in the end, the US met the North
Vietnamese government to negotiate peace
in 1973. And the country remained
divided into North and South exactly the
way it was before the war broke out. In
other words, the Vietnam War ultimately
ended not in a victory, but in a
stalemate. And that stalemate cost
American taxpayers billions of dollars
and the American population almost
60,000 lives, not to mention the
millions of Vietnamese who had perished
in the conflict as well. Now, there were
plenty of effects of this war, including
a growing division in American culture
and the credibility gap that I mentioned
a second ago. But here, I just want to
focus on one major effect, namely the
debate over the proper extent of
executive power. So, remember, this is
now the second American war since World
War II ended that was fought without a
declaration of war from Congress. Like,
Harry Truman was so intent on containing
the spread of communism in Korea that he
bypassed Congress and deployed American
troops with the authorization of the
United Nations. And then, the Gulf of
Tonkin Resolution further removed
wartime authority from Congress and gave
the president essentially a blank check
to do whatever he wanted. And that got a
sizable portion of the American public
more than a little twitchy. They seemed
to remember that the framers of the
Constitution put the power to declare
war into the hands of Congress precisely
so that a single president couldn't just
decide to risk American lives in combat
and spend billions of tax dollars
provided by working Americans. No, by
design, that was a decision that had to
be made by the people and their
congressional representatives, not just
one guy in a suit. And so, because the
Vietnam War was so deeply contentious,
Congress sought to take back their power
from the executive branch. To that end,
they passed the War Powers Resolution in
1973, which severely curtailed
presidential powers in making war. So,
it required the president to consult
Congress within 48 hours of deploying
troops, and then if those troops
remained deployed for 60 days, then they
could only remain if Congress officially
declared war. And that's great and all,
you know, Congress, you get your power
back. But in reality, it was much more
complicated. For example, once troops
are in the field responding to some
conflict, it would be very difficult for
Congress just to cut off their funding
after 60 days if they didn't agree with
the president's justification for
sending them. But regardless, this push
and pull between executive and
congressional power to wage war will
continue up to this present day. Well,
okay, you can click here to watch all my
other Unit 8 videos or you can click
here to grab my A push Heimler review
guide, which has everything you need to
study as fast as possible. I'm glad you
came around and I'll catch on the
flip-flop. Heimler out.